Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 3 -- Letters to Franklin 1778 April-December Mss.B.F85inventory03
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 3 -- Letters to Franklin
1778 April-December
Mss.B.F85inventory03
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
1405 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Tucker, Samuel. Bordeaux
    Scope and Contents note
    His arrival after a fatiguing passage of forty-two days; sends by Captain Richard Palmer a copy of his instructions and signals; desires to know his further destination; busy getting the ship in readiness for sea; captured the ship Marthy from London bound for New York; has only one lieutenant at present; deisres advice as to appointing others.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778? Monday 4; A.L. in 3d P. 2p. (In French.); Brillon, Mme
    Recommending a friend, M. Hennet, who had furnished some supplies of arms for Congress and who wishes to offer his services to some gentlemen from Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Chasseneuil, —, marquise de. Saint Foy-la-Grande
    Reminds Franklin of a half promise to give her the address of a compatriot in America to whom she could sent her wines to sell on commission.
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Vincent, G. fils. St. Malo
    Enclosing a letter from one John Johnstone said to be an American but has the misfortune to make one of the crew on board an English cutter, detained for twelve weeks in the harbor; begs to be informed if he is really an American.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 2; L.S. 4p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Expressing great anger and indignation at being kept in ignorance of M. Gérard's mission to America and also of Mr. Deane's departure.
    General note
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 257, Note).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Delaire, -----. La Rochelle
    His joy at the alliance between the United Provinces and France; his knowledge of the theory of commerce; his familiarity with languages; desires to form an establishment at La Rochelle for the instruction of young men in the knowledge of commerce; wishes Franklin to become the patron of the establishment and to recommend it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 2; A.L.S. 3p.; de Corcelles, Polier. Lausanne
    Plan of several Swiss gentlemen to raise a regiment of 1,500 infantry to serve in America. Suggests their being raised in the name of France, the States' new ally; secrecy to be observed; puts himself in Franklin's hands on condition that he is assured a suitable rank in the forthcoming levy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Information received from M. Grand that Mr. Williams continues drawing on the public funds, though he has received no orders to answer his drafts; has not been consulted in this matter, but considers it an irregularity.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 3; A.L.S. 5p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Extracts from foreign letters; war with Austria inevitable; France endeavoring indirectly to keep peace between Russia and the Porte. Rumored withdrawal of Lord Stormont from the French Court. General opinion in Rotterdam that England will be forced to recognize the independence of the Colonies. Desirability of a commercial treaty between Holland and America. Recent agitation in Holland over the augmenting of their land forces; attitude of M. de Berkenro[o]de, Dutch Minister to France. Conversation held with M. Van Berkel; assurances of Holland's perfect neutrality; urges the wisdom of profiting by the friendship and commerce of the United States. Advises their writing an official letter to the Grand Pensionnaire announcing the treaty of the United States with France and stating America's friendly attitude towards Holland.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Ridley, Matthew
    Introducing Mr. Ebenezer Platt, whose sufferings in the cause of America are known to Franklin; lately released from prison and married to a daughter of Mrs. Wright; their only mode of returning to America is through France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 3; L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Gov Thomas. Annapolis
    Notifying him of the appointment of Joshua Johnson as agent for Maryland in soliciting military stores.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Arrival at Bordeaux of John Adams, Esq., who sets off at once for Paris. News of various vessels. Desirability of France announcing a fixed time when a convoy will attend the ships destined for North America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    Compelled again to request the explanation so often promised him; also the reasons in writing why the alterations in the treaty of commerce were not to be communicated to him.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Ranger," Cameret
    Is now perfectly ready to proceed with the Fortunée of thirty-eight guns and the tender sent by Comte d'Orvilliers; deeply concerned at the time lost; will make the better use of that to come. Concerning the large frigate built for America at Amsterdam; hopes to find her ready to his return. Saluted the French flag at Brest with thirteen guns and received in return two guns less; possible reasons for this.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 4; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Reminds him of his promise to bring Mr. Adams to dine at his house and requests Franklin to return him the Spanish grammar and Gibbons's History of Rome.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 4; L.S. 2p.; Dalkerque, De Lattre. Dunkirk
    Acknowledging his letter of the 8th of February, enclosing two letters of recommendation for the captain of his frigate, la Comtesse de Brionne; she sailed for America on the 2d inst., well armed and richly loaded.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 4; A.L.S. 4p.; Müller de la Piolotte, —. Lure
    Has charge of glass works at Champagney; his experience and knowledge of the manufacture of glass; desires to establish glass-works in America; lays this project in detail before Franklin and asks his advice; his reasons for wishing to take this step.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. Hawkins of Carolina.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Not knowing anything of the transactions referred to him, cannot judge whether it is fit to discharge the enclosed accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Montgomery, Robert.
    Has been established in the above port of Spain twelve months and has acquired business and consequence. Afraid if Spain declares war against England, he will be treated as a British subject; begs Franklin to send him a certificate of his identity as an American; encloses a paper to prove his nationality; refers to Mr. Thomas Morris for particulars.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1778 April 5; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Schönfeld, -----, baron de.
    Sending Franklin a letter from the directors of one of the most reliable manufactories of fire-arms in Germany.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Concerning repairs, etc., on the ship Boston; Captain Tucker's action in not reporting the arrival to the Admiralty Board; his salute to the Castle not returned, no instructions having been received from the Board of War on that head. English fleet still lying between Capes Ortegal and Finisterre. The Spanish fleet expected shortly from Cuba.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Pommereuille, --, sieur de. Fougères
    Concerning the hard case of his brother, M. de Martigny, who followed M. du Coudray to America, in hopes of aiding in the defense of liberty; his subsequent disappointment and return to France; expenses incurred; begs Franklin to obtain from M. de Sartine the settlements of his brother's just demands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Champigny, Jean Bochard de. Amsterdam
    Reasons for sending his second volume of the History of England before the first one, which will follow later together with the first two volumes of his Translation of the History of Denmark. Congratulates him on his new diginity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    On the strength of Mr. Hancock's letter to Franklin in favor of Mr. Cooper, will advance that young gentleman the necessaries he stands in need of.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Brongniart, Antoine Louis. Paris
    When he will make certain experiments in electricity; hopes Franklin will have sufficient leisure to attend. Successful treatment of certain sick people by means of the electric fluid.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 7.; A.L. 4P.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Extracts from German letters; warlike preparations throughout the country. Account of a considerable quantity of cannon and arms for sale. Further suggestions for their official letter to the Grand Pensionnaire; desirability of crushing the English party in Holland. Intrigues in Dutch politics.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 7; A.N. in 3d P. 1P.; de Sarsfield, M
    Requesting Franklin to be at his house at 2 o'clock for dinner, as Prince de Aingry will be there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 8.; A.L.S. 2p.; Deane, Silas. Aix
    Their arrival at Aix, Begs Franklin to make his adicus to certain friends at Paris, which he failed to do from lack of time. Thanking him for the friendship and confidence he has honored him with and for the honorable testimony he has given him to Congress. Wishing him all happiness and prosperity.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 230.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Beaugeard, Desegray Jr., St. Malo
    Congratulations on their glorious transactions with the French Ministry. An English frigate seen lately in their neighborhood. Enclosing a letter from Mr. J. D. Schweighauser in which he seems to have been appointed to represent the American agent in Brittany; desires to know if that letter is comfortable to their orders.
    [Copy of M. Schweighauser's letter in French, enclosed.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the unfortunate condition of Captain Collas, the husband of Jenny Mecom, now a prisoner in England. His late indisposition; expects to set out for Paris shortly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr.George Readhead, of South Carolina, and Mr. Craig, of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Roberdeau, Jacques-Dominique
    His delay in answering Franklin's favor of February 21st due to the mislaying of General Roberdeau's letter; sends it now. Congratulations on the success of his endeavors for his country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Farry ?,-----. Chateauneuf
    His experience as surgeon on his Majesty's ships; desires to be of service to the American people; proposes certain conditions under which he is willing to practice medicine in the Colonies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Begging his favorable attention to the request of the American captains for a convoy off the French coast. Constant applications for wages and prize-money, by Frenchmen who served on board the Lexington. Mr. M[orris] sold what was brought in here and the money is the Lord knows where. Wishes the Commissioners had given up what was carried to their credit and taken the loss of Mr. M[orris]'s conduct on themselves, it would have saved an infinity of credit which the service has suffered. Question of Mr. William Lee having given his appointment to Mr. Schweighauser; reasons why he resents this; action he has taken in the matter.
  - to The Ministers Plenipotentiary of the United States at the Court of France., 1778 April 9; L.S. 2p.; The Captains of American Merchant Vessels at Nantes and Neighboring Ports. Nantes
    Requesting them to apply to the French Court for a convoy off the coast sufficient to protect the American vessels.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 9; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Navy Board of the Eastern Department. Boston
    Encloses gazettes to date. Cannot risk other packages.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Lee, William. Frankfort-sur-le-Maine
    The Presence of any one on their part at Berlin will not be of any use. The Vienna scheme will be prosecuted; England will not declare war until Burgoyne and his troops are got safe, lest they should be intercepted. Proposes a plan to send La Motte Picquet with certain ships to be joined at Boston by others, the whole to proceed immediately to Halifax which must fall into their hands with all the naval stores.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 10.; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Clerc de St. Etrain, --, abbé de. Paris
    Asking for the letters of recommendation he promised to M. Mereau de Mannevan, who has left for Amsterdam.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Guillaud, Claud. Cadiz
    England has altered her Mediterranean passports, so that the ones they had before the war rendered useless. Plan of a certain merchant to enter into peace negotiations with the Emperor of Morocco; he has written Franklin more particularly on this subject; it will all tend to the prosperity and happiness of America. Captain Cunningham still at Cadiz.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 10; A.L.S. 8p.; Toustain, Charles-Gaspard de Toustain-Richebourg, vicomte de. Josselin
    Concerning his paper, "A Challenge to Lord Suffolk," and other similar reflections and explanations; his desire to enter the American service under certain conditions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 10; A.L.S. 2 p.; Gravier, -----. Marseilles
    Wishes to settle in America. Inquires as to what assistance he might hope for.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 11; A.L.S. 2p.; d'Alignac, -----. Clermont-Ferrand
    Begging for information of one of his relatives, named le Chevalier de Pontgibaut, who left Nantes on October 11th to pass into the service of America with letter to M. de Lafayette and to General Conway; his father's anxiety at receiving no news of him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Madden, Jean Butler. Nantes
    Considerable commerce between France and America; need of an interpreter at Nantes to assist the French and American captains in their business relations; offers himself for the position and begs Franklin to obtain it for him from the French Admiral.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 11; A.L.S. 3p.; de St Lambert, Aubin. Termonde
    Has served in the French navy as captain of various vessels; desires to pass into the service of the Colonies; his knowledge of navigation and acquaintance with several languages; certificates he can furnish.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Hutton, James
    Introducing Mr. D'Aguiton, of Geneva; he has an affair of merchandise to settle with a Mr. Heywood, of Paris; announcing the death of Mr. Falconer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 11; A.L.S. 2p.; De Gruyere, -----. Paris
    A note enclosing the letter from Wyss.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumagny, -----. Partenay
    His enthusiasm for the American cause; desires to serve in the army of the republic.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Has just learned that Mr. Deane has left Paris; desires orders as to the providing for American prisoners and seamen who may, in future, arrive at Dunkrik. Congratulating Mr. Adams on his safe arrival in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Serrier,-------. Damvillers
    Desiring to know Franklin's remedy for dropsy, which he has read about in the newspapers; one of his parishoners has been a sufferer from the disease for twenty-eight years. In exchange for this important service, will bestow on Franklin the title of benefactor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Mostowski, Paul Michael (Pawel Michal), "prince". Paris
    Desires a personal interview; begs him to name the day and hour.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Döhren, Jacques von. Hamburg
    Offers his services to the Republic in case the Commissioners see fit to establish an agency at Hamburg; advantages resulting from such an office; should this idea meet with their approval, has a plan for the establishment of an American depot at Hamburg.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Deane, 1778 April 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    The Duchesse de Grammont set sail on the 7th inst. Question of paying wages to a French sailor who escaped from prison after being taken in the Lexington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 14; A.L.S. 4p.; Valltravers, Rodolph. Bienne
    Desires news of the safe arrival of certain important letters. Trusts the treaty between France and America does not preclude Great Britain forever from proper connection with the States. Suggests an alliance between the thirteen Cantons and the thirteen United States. His plan for eliminating poverty in the United States.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Lee., 1778 April 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Captain Tucker almost ready to sail. Present unsettled state creates great stagnation in trade; many opulent merchants whose operations are suspended until war is declared or peace established.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Penet, P. Paris
    Sends a memoir, forwarded to him by an American captain; desires to know if the Minister of Marine will grant the demands in the aforesaid memoir; advantages to be gained from such concessions, such as the greater safety to their vessels, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Lugny, — de. Bordeaux
    Is a geographical engineer in the above city; if, by these means he can render himself useful to the States, offers Franklin his services.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Caille, D'audibert. Cadiz
    Concerning peace between United States and Emperor of Morocco.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Reynolds, John. Paris
    As recommended by him, he wrote to Mr. Jonathan Williams at Nantes for information as to certain American articles which he had a clear channel of introducing into England; will proceed on his return journey the following night.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 14; L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Freté, M. and Mme. de
    Hopes that Messrs. Franklin have not forgotten their engagement to dine with them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Látáche, Jean. Angoulême
    His plan of establishing a manufactory of maps in America; the means to be employed in its formation and the advantages to accrue to the Colonies from such an establishment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Prat, Antoine F. Lyons
    Begs Franklin to procure him a position as secretary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 15; A.L.S. 1p.; L'Enfant, -----. Paris
    Begging Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to his son in America; Mlle. Basseporte joins with him in imploring Franklin's favor for this only child.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roy, -----. Cherbourg
    Concerning John Burnell, captain of the privateer Montgomery, now in prison at Plymouth. Failure on the part of M. Dulonprey to answer his demands for the money due to Burnell; applies to Franklin for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 8; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Turgot, Anne-Robert-Jacques, baron de l'Aulne. Paris
    Reminding Franklin of his engagement to dine with him; if Mr. Adams, the new Commissioner has arrived, desires his company also.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 16; L.S. 2p.; Sarsfield, Jacques-Hyacinthe, vicomte de (Guy-Claude's brother). Paris
    Asks Franklin's interest and patronage on behalf of M. Somers, the son of a rich merchant of Lille who wishes to send some goods into America. Prevented from seeing Franklin for some time, owing to illness; is about to leave for the Chateau de Marly where he and Mme. de Sarsfield unite in hoping Franklin will visit them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Tarteron, -----. Mende
    An ode to Franklin; compares him to Solon; the glorious treaty which he arranged with France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 16; A.L.S. 6p.; Monts, Chevalier de
    Describing an invention of his for writing secret despatches on cotton cloth where it is invisible until made to appear by the use of certain chemicals; desires to make a present of this discovery to America.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Lovell, James. Yorktown
    Notice of the authorization of William Bingham to draw bills of exchange upon the Commissioners.
    (In triplicate.)
    Printed in Wharton's Diplom. Corres. of the Amer. Rev., II, 553.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Dupont, —, fils (lawyer). Colmar
    Has not the honor of being known to Franklin, but M. Voltaire, the genius of France, is an old friend of his father and M. Gérard knows his family well; desires to enter the American army.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 16; A.L.S. James Lovell. 1p.; The Continental Congress, Committee for Foreign Affairs. Yorktown
    Resolve of Congress, authorizing William Bingham, agent of the United States at Martinique, to draw on the Commissioners for certain sums. An uncommon fatality has attended their despatches; anxious for news.
  - to the American Commissioners., 1778 April 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Deane, Simeon. Falmouth
    Announcing his safe arrival and his immediate departure for Congress. No intelligence received as yet of the Continental fleet which left France in February. The spirits of the people very high; makes us doubt that the good news which he bears will give the greatest satisfaction. Report of the taking of Quebec, though it is not confirmed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 17; L.S. 2p.; Irwin, J. Marseilles
    Is a British subject and an ex-officer in the English army. Wishes to be allowed to remain in France with his family. Offers to act as Consul for the United States at Nantes or Bordeaux.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 April 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Begging them to procure the enlargement of one, James Wiggins, sailor, a native of America and now detained on board the Hawk, a privateer belonging to London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; d'Amraff, Caetanus. Paris
    His wife and two children in great distress; applies to Franklin for help; knows eight languages; is versed in art, music and commerce; desires Franklin to procure him some position either in America or Europe.
    (In Latin.)
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Deane, 1778 April 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Questions of repairing arms and shipping them to America. Congratulating Mr. Adams on his safe arrival.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Boeckmann, I. L. Carlsrube
    Asking Franklin's advice about the placing of a lightning conductor which the Margrave of Baden desires to put on his chateau.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Jay, Sir James. Paris
    Again requests the information he desired.